New York City Mayor's Advisory Transit Committee Hearing Transcripts and Records 5251
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
New York City Mayor's Advisory Transit Committee Hearing Transcripts and Records
1939-1947
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
New York City Mayor's Advisory Transit Committee
Hoffman, Anna Rosenberg, 1902-1983.
Rosenman, Samuel I. (Samuel Irving), 1896-1973.
Kheel, Theodore Woodrow.
Mulroney, Edward P.
Knowlton, Thomas Anson.
Friedman, Clara H.
5251
2 cubic feet
2 linear ft.
Records (documents).
This collection contains materials produced by the New York City Mayor's Advisory Transit Committee and submissions to the committee from the various parties involved in the mediation. These records include transcripts of the hearings, exhibits from labor unions, submissions from the New York City Transit Authority, correspondence of committee members, and drafts of committee documents.
5621927
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
E. Parker, April 12, 2017
EAD encoding:
E. Parker, April 12, 2017
Biographical / Historical
The New York City Transit Board was established in 1924 as the operating agency for the New York City mass transit system. In 1932, the Transit Board completed the construction of the Independent Subway [IND] and its employees became part of the Competitive Civil Service System in 1935.
There were two private companies providing subway service in New York at this time: the Brooklyn-Manhattan Transit Company [BRT] and the Interborough Rapid Transit Company [IRT]. Their employees had negotiated system-wide closed shop agreements with the Transport Workers' Union [TWU] in 1937, except for motormen and signal maintainers. They were represented by the Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers [BLE] and the Brotherhood of Railroad Signalmen [BRS], respectively.
In 1940, New York City purchased the BMT and the IRT and as part of the purchase agreed to respect the contracts of the three unions, which were set to expire in 1941. However, the relationship between the City and the unions degenerated and the TWU made two separate strike threats. The mayor of New York, William O'Dwyer, eventually responded to these threats by creating the Mayor's Advisory Transit Committee in 1946. The committee was charged with studying the issues and making recommendations regarding working conditions, wages, and labor relations with the NYC Transit Board. The chairman of the board was Arthur S. Meyer. The other members of the committee were Theodore W. Kheel, Edward P. Mulrooney, Anna M. Hoffman (nee Rosenberg), and Samuel I. Rosenman. Dr. Thomas Knowlton, United States Conciliation Service, and Clara Friedman (nee Handleman), labor arbitrator, served as executive secretary and committee economist, respectively.
The central issues addressed were the desirabiliity and permissibility of collective bargaining, the process for resolving grievances, the legality of public employees striking, and monetary issues concerning both wages and maintenance of an extensive transit system. Hearings were held in the spring and summer of 1946.
The final report of the committee was delivered to Mayor O'Dwyer on September 9, 1946.
Scope and Contents
Inclusive date range: 1937 -1947
Bulk date: 1946
This collection consists of records submitted to and created by the New York City's Mayor's Advisory Committee. The collection is divided into four series, listed below, to help distinguish the creators of the records in this collection. "Series I: Hearing Transcripts" consists of fourteen bound volumes conaining the transcripts of the thirteen public hearings held in March, April, and May 1946 and for the hearing in June 1946 held with the Board of Transportation. "Series II: Union Exhibits and Submissions" consists of memoranda, demands, briefs, supplemental briefs, exhibits, and other submissions made by the sixteen unions representing the employees in the NYC Transit System. In addition to the records of these sixteen organizations which appeared at the hearings, this series also conatins the briefs of an additional seven labor orgnizations which did not participate in the hearings, but did file their papers with the Committee (for a complete list of these organiations, see pp. iii-iv in the final report of the Committee). "Series III: Board of Transportation Exhibits and Submissions" consists of the Board of Transportation [BoT] response to the demands of its employees in a memorandum with exhibits and additional submissions with data that the BoT alleged supported their position in denying the demands of their employees. "Series IV: Mayor's Committee Drafts, Correspondence, and Reports" consists of the records generated by the Committee itself. These papers include multiple drafts of the final report submitted to the Mayor, detailed analysis of monetary matters and labor relations with regard to civil service employees in other municipalities as they relate to the demands of the employees, annotated copies of civil service laws, correspondence between committee members, and a copy of the final published report of the Mayor's Advisory Transit Committee.
Series I: Hearing Transcripts, 1946 (Box 1, Folders 1 -13)
Series II: Union Exhibits and Submissions, 1939-1946 (Box 1, Folders 14-28)
Series III: Board of Transportation Exhibits and Submissions, 1943-1946 (Box 2, Folders 1a-4)
Series IV: Mayor's Committee Drafts, Correspondence, and Reports, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folders 5-18)
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5321: U.S. Department of Labor Wage and Hour and Public Contracts Division Special Industry Committee #12 Records 5252: Arthur Meyer Papers 5114: New York City Transit Authority Fact Finding Panel Records 5118: New York City Board of Transportation and the Transport Workers Union Records
Arrangement
Series I: Hearing Transcripts, 1946
Series II: Union Exhibits and Submissions, 1939-1946
Series III: Board Of Transportation Exhibits and Submissions, 1943-1946
Series IV: Mayor's Committee Drafts, Correspondence, and Reports, 1946-1947
Transport Workers Union of America.; Brotherhood of Railroad Signalmen.; Civil Service Forum.; AFSCME.; New York City Board of Transportation; Collective bargaining -- Government employees -- New York; Strikes and lockouts -- Civil service -- New York; Transport workers -- New York (State) -- New York; Wages -- Local transit -- New York (State) -- New York; Meyer, Arthur S. (Arthur Simon), 1880-1955.; New York (N.Y.) Mayor's Advisory Transit Committee; New York (N.Y.). Transit Police Department -- Employees; Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers (U.S.)
5621927
- Series I: Hearing Transcripts, 1946
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains fourteen volumes transcribing the hearings held by the Mayor's Advisory Committee. Thirteen hearings were open to the public. Nine of these hearings, held between March 12 and April 14, 1946, were concerned with monetary matters, such as wages, vacation, promotions, and holidays. Four hearings concerning labor relations were held with the employees organizations between May 15 and May 20, 1946. Finally, a hearing with the BoT regarding labor relations was held on June 4, 1946.
  - Mayor's Advisory Transit Committee Preliminary Hearing Transcript. Pages 1-34 and Pages 35-139., 1946 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    In the Matter of The Board of Transportation of the City of New York and The Transport Workers' Union.
  - Mayor's Advisory Transit Committee Preliminary Hearing Transcript. Pages 140-219., 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    In the Matter of The Board of Transportation of the City of New York and New York Transit Police Association; New York City Police Sergeants' Association; The Transport Workers' Union.
  - Mayor's Advisory Transit Committee Preliminary Hearing Transcript. Pages 220-326., 1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    In the Matter of The Board of Transportation of the City of New York and Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers; Brotherhood of R.R. Signalmen of America, New York Transit Police Association; New York City Police Sergeants' Association; The Transport Workers Union.
  - Mayor's Advisory Transit Committee Preliminary Hearing Transcript. Pages 327-465., 1946 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    In the Matter of The Board of Transportation of the City of New York and Civil Service Forum; Claim Examiners, IRT & BMT, Grades 1, 2, & 3; Claim Examiners, BMT, Grade 2; Provisional Claim Examiners, et al.
  - Mayor's Advisory Transit Committee Preliminary Hearing Transcript. Pages 466-595., 1946 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    In the Matter of The Board of Transportation of the City of New York and American Federation of Municipal Transit Workers, Local 21193, A.F.L., et al.
  - Mayor's Advisory Transit Committee Preliminary Hearing Transcript. Pages 596-659, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    In the Matter of The Board of Transportation of the City of New York and Board of Transportation, Local 624; American Federation of State, County, & Municipal Employees, AFL; et al.
  - Mayor's Advisory Transit Committee Preliminary Hearing Transcript. Pages 660-806, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    In the Matter of The Board of Transportation of the City of New York and Civil service Technical Guild, et al.
  - Mayor's Advisory Transit Committee Preliminary Hearing Transcript. Pages 807-847., 1946 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    In the Matter of The Board of Transportation of the City of New York and The Transport Workers' Union, et al.
  - Mayor's Advisory Transit Committee Preliminary Hearing Part II, Transcript Pages 1-128., 1946 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    In the Matter of The Board of Transportation of the City of New York and The American Federation of Municipal Transit Workers, Local 21193, et al.
  - Mayor's Advisory Transit Committee Preliminary Hearing Part II, Transcript. Pages 129-226, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    In the Matter of The Board of Transportation of the City of New York and Board of Transportation Local 624, American Federation of State, County, and Municipal Employees, AFL; Civil Service Forum, et al.
  - Mayor's Advisory Transit Committee Preliminary Hearing Part II, Transcript. Pages 227-402, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    In the Matter of The Board of Transportation of the City of New York and Civil Service Forum; Civil Service Technical Guild; Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers; Brotherhood of R.R. Signalmen; New York Transit Police Association; Yardmasters; Association of Administrative and Clerical Employees; Independent Division of Train Dispatchers Grievance Committee.
  - Mayor's Advisory Transit Committee Preliminary Hearing, Part II, Transcript. Pages 403-610., 1946 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Mayor's Advisory Transit Committee Preliminary Hearing, Part II, Transcript. Pages 611-739., 1946 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series II: Union Exhibits and Submissions, 1939-1946
  This series consists of the various papers filed by the employee organizations. The papers both list the demands of the employees and provide supporting materials as exhibits to bolster their claims. Of interest in this series are the various agreements and contracts between carriers and labor unions submitted as exhibits, statistical information on wage rates for various professions, both in New York City and in the rest of the United States, and crime statistics for the New York Transit system provided by the unions representing the Transit Police and the Transit Police Sergeants' Association. An annotated index for these exhibits is also located in this series.
  - American Federation of Municipal Transit Workers (MTW), Local 21193, AFL. Exhibits and Summary Points in Support of Demands, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - AFSCME, Board of Transportation Local 624: Memorandum and Exhibits in Support of Demands and Exhibits, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers: Letter and Exhibits in Support of Demands, 1939-1946 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Exhibits consist of agreements between the BLE and various carriers such as the BMT, the Central of New Jersey, and the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad.
  - Brotherhood of Railroad Signalmen of America: Demands, Brief (exhibits included therein), and Supplemental Brief, 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Lodge 113, Brooklyn, New York.
  - Civil Service Forum: Demands, Brief, Exhibits, and related correspondence, 1941-1946 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Civil Service Technical Guild: Demands, Brief, and Exhibits, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Claim Examiners (All who appeared at Hearing): Demands, Memoranda of Support, and Exhibits. Association of Administrative and Clerical Employees: Demands and Exhibits., 1946 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Claims Examiners, grades 1, 2, 3, and 4, from both the BMT and IRT systems, working in the trial and legal divisions.
  - New York City Transit Police Association: Briefs (containing Demands) and Exhibits, 1941-1946 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Exhibits include statistics for subway crime in 1945 and 1946
  - New York City Transit Police Sergeants' Association: Demands, Brief, and Exhibits, 1941-1946 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Exhibits includes statistics about police activity, 1941-1945
  - Independent Dispatchers; Yardmasters IND Div.; Association of Engineers & Architects- State, County, & Municipal Workers of America, CIO; Motorman Instructor's Grievance Committee, IND Div.: Demands & Exhibits, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Submissions, No Hearings, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    from Committee of Clerical, Engineering & Administrative Employees; Stenographers & Typists - BMT & IRT, Grades 1, 2, & 3; Assistant Counsels- Grade 4, BMT Trials Dept.; Train Masters IND Div.
  - The Transit Workers' Union of Greater New York: Exhibits and Supplemental Exhibits, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Indexes for "Submission, No Hearing" File and for "Hearing" Files, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Summary of Monetary Demands Submitted to the Mayor's Advisory Transit Committee (Part 1), 1946 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    On behalf of the organizations representing the employees.
  - Report to the Mayor's Advisory Committee on Wages and Working Conditions of New York Board of Transportation Employees (Part 2: Index of Tables 1-23)., 1946 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Series III: Board Of Transportation Exhibits and Submissions, 1943-1946
  This Series consists of memoranda submitted by the BoT to refute the demands of the employees. Included in the exhibits are financial data regarding the maintenance and operating costs of the Transit System and about the working conditions of its employees. Of note in these exhibits is the attention paid to the legality of civil service employees having collective bargaining rights, whether they have a right to strike, and the rules and regulations their employees are subject to.
  - Memorandum on Behalf of Board of Transportation and Supporting Exhibits 1-4, 8-9. [folder 1 of 2], 1946 (Box 2, Folder 1a)
  - Memorandum on Behalf of Board of Transportation and Supporting Exhibits 1-4, 8-9. [folder 2 of 2], 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 1b)
  - Board of Transportation of the City of New York Submission: "Report Including Analysis of Operations of the New York City Transit System for Five years Ended June 30, 1945" (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Board of Transportation of the City of New York: submissions re monetary matters, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Board of Transportation of the City of New York submission regarding operating costs of transit facilities, wages paid, and system maintenance, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Includes correspondence with Thomas A. Knowlton, Executive Secretary of the Mayor's Advisory Committee
- Series IV: Mayor's Committee Drafts, Correspondence, and Reports, 1946-1947
  This series consists of the records generated by the Committee itself. The majority of the records are various drafts of the final report, with different committee members adding their edits and annotations to the others' drafts. Also found in this series are materials the committee used for research, such as agreements from other cities, copies of New York State laws, and additional data from the BoT that was submitted upon request of the committee. The correspondence of the committee is found in this series, and in addition to documenting the minutiae of being part of such a committee, there are also newspaper clippings, drafts, supplemental data, and communications with New York politicians, including Mayor O'Dwyer.
  - Annotated Drafts Marked "Discard", 1946 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Includes duplicate drafts with annotations from different committee members
  - Civil Service Laws in regard to Demands, drafts, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Annotated by committee members
  - Executive Secretary Thomas A. Knowlton's Analysis, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Includes "Digest of Testimony" and annotated memos from the committee.
  - Drafts of Committee's Analysis and Recommendations, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Includes correspondence between committee members
  - Labor Relations Papers regarding civil service employees in New York State, 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Contains annotated document, "Presentation to Mayor's Advisory Transit Committee of the Position of the Board of Transportation with Respect to Labor Relations."
  - Labor Relations Papers regarding trade unions for government employees and legality of strikes, 1939-1946 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Includes reports commissioned by New York City mayors regarding labor relations in the City's transit system
  - Report Covering the Study of Contracts, etc. of Various Municipalities and an Itemization of the Categories Into Which They Respectively Fall, with contracts from other municipalities., 1943-1946 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Original "My (Arthur S. Meyer) Draft" and "Sam's (Judge Samuel I. Rosenman) Draft", 1946 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Report of the Mayor's Advisory Transit Committee: draft of gratitude memo and proposed changes to the report by committee members, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Report of the Mayor's Advisory Transit Committee: final draft, committee recommendations and unpublished statement from the Committee, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Report of the Mayor's Advisory Transit Committee to Honorable William O'Dwyer, Mayor of the City of New York, September 9, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Mayor's Advisory Transit Committee, Correspondence, File 1, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Mayor's Advisory Transit Committee, Correspondence, File 2, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Requests for Copies of Mayor's Advisory Committee Report, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 18)